Guide to the Arna Bontemps Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Arna Bontemps Collection
1934-1957
JWJ MSS 6
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4
(6 boxes)
The Arna Bontemps Collections contains writings and correspondence presented to the James Weldon Johnson Collection by Mr. Bontemps.
Bontemps, Arna, 1902-1973
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Arna Bontemps Collection contains items presented to the James Weldon Johnson Collection by Mr. Bontemps.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
ARNA BONTEMPS (1902-1973)
Arna Bontemps was a teacher and writer whose novel God Sends Sunday appeared at the end of the Harlem Renaissance in 1931. He continued writing and editing anthologies and served as librarian at Fisk University.
Scope and Contents
The papers contains materials documenting the life of Arna Bontemps, including Series I, Correspondence, and Series II, Writings.
African American authors -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Bontemps, Arna, 1902-1973
- Correspondence, 1942-45, n.d.; Series I
  - Blount, Mildred E., 1942-45, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes letter from Ruby Bontemps and two autobiographical sketches To: 6 / From: 1
  - Butain, Anne M., 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    To: 2 / From: 0
  - Cambell, E. Simms, 1944-45 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    To: 2 / From: 1
  - Cayton, Horace R., 1944 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    To: 1 / From: 0
  - Collins, Leslie, 1944 Oct 19 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes notes on interview of Mrs. Jelliffe To: 1 / From: 0
  - Conroy, Jack, c. 1944 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Correspondence re: They Seek A City To: 21 / From: 9
  - Conroy, Jack, c. 1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Correspondence re: They Seek A City To: 25 / From: 26
  - Conroy, Jack, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Correspondence re: Slappy Hooper To: 3 / From: 0
  - Dabney, Wendell P., 1944 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    To: 5 / From: 0
  - Davis, Benjamin O. Sr., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Fragment To: 1 / From: 0
  - Davis, Mrs. Benjamin O. Jr., 1944, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    To: 4 / From: 2
  - Dixon, Dean, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Includes short description of the Dixon counting method. To: 2 / From: 1
  - Henry, Algernon P., 1944 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    To: 1 / From: 1
  - Houghton Mifflin Co., 1945 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Hughes, Langston, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Carbon of letter to Guggenheim Foundation re: AWB
  - Jackman, Harold, 1934-42 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Original AWB letters To: 0 / From: 6
  - Lem and Ed (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Correspondence re: St. Louis Woman To: 1 / From: 1
  - LuValle, James E., 1944 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    To: 2 / From: 2
  - May, Mrs. Emmett, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    To: 3 / From: 2
  - Moore, Alfred D., 1944-45, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    To: 21 / From: 1
  - Palfi, Marion, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Frederick A. Stokes Company, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Letter to Maxim Lieber re: AWB
  - Trammell, Guy R., 1945 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    To: 3 / From: 0
  - Van Vechten, Carl, 1941-47 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Walker, Margaret, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    To: 0 / From: 1
  - Walters, Vernon N., 1945 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Watkins, Sylvestre, 1942, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Watson, Douglas C., 1944 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Young, P. Bernard Jr., 1944 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Writings, Series II
  - Black Thunder
    - Typescript, corrected of unfinished rewrite of book, with revisions and explanatory note by AWB (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Dramatization by Roland Mulhauser, typescript, corrected, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      Includes: explanatory note by AWB
  - Bubber Joins the Band
    - Typescript, carbon, [ca. 1932-33] (Box 1, Folder 32)
      Unpublished children's story with explanatory note by AWB
  - Drums at Dusk
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Purple Island, Box 1, folder 36
  - The Fast Sooner Hound
    - Typescript corrected, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      First version of children's story By AWB and Jack Conroy with explanatory note by AWB
  - Father of the Blues
    - Typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 34)
      Part of AWB's version of W. C. Handy's autobiography with explanatory notes by AWB
  - God Sends Sunday
    See: St. Louis Woman, Box 2, folder 37
  - Poor Frizzly Chicken
    - Typescript carbon, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      Unpublished children's story, original unrevised version, with illustrations and explanatory note by AWB
  - Purple Island
    - Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 36)
      First draft of book Drums at Dusk with explanatory note by AWB
  - St. Louis Woman
    - Typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 37)
      Play by AWB and Countée Cullen with revisions, an explanatory note by AWB, and inscription by Countée Cullen
    - Mixture of typescript and carbon versions, corrected (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 40)
      With new Prologue by Langston Hughes
    - Holograph notes for revision, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Holograph and typescript revisions and rewrites (Box 2, Folder 42-45)
    - "How 'St. Louis Woman' Was Born" handwritten draft of publicity statement, 1946 Jan 31 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Theatre programs, 1945-52, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Slappy Hooper
    - Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 48)
      Children's story by AWB and Jack Conroy
    - Typescipt and carbon revisions (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - The Story of the Negro
    - Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 51-52)
    - Index (on 3 x 5 cards) with corrections (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Galley proofs, corrected, 1947-48 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - They Seek A City
    - Notes, drafts, outlines, etc., 1945, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - First draft, typsecript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 56-58)
      Includes: second versions of some chapters
    - First draft, typsecript, corrected, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 59-61)
    - Final draft, typescript, corrected, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 62-66)
      With printer's notes and author's notes
    - Bibliography and index, corrected (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Galley proofs, corrected, n.d.
  - Tom-Tom Treasures
    - Typescript, corrected, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 69)
      Unpublished children's story
  - "The Two Harlems"
    - Typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 70)
      article for American Scholar
  - "Remarks in Presenting..."
    Full title: "Remarks in Presenting American Library Association's Liberty and Justice Award in Imaginative Literature to James Thurber"
    - Typescript carbon, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - We Have Tomorrow
    - Research notes, clippings, and typed manuscript of biographical sketch of Dean Dixon (Box 5, Folder 72)
    - First draft, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 73-74)
      Includes: biographical sketches of Benjamin Davis, E. Simms Campbell, Mildred E. Blount, Emmett M. May, Algernon R. Henry, Hazel Scott, Mildred Blount, Dean Dixon, Benjamin Davis, Horace Cayton and Revels Cayton, Jimmy LuValle, Douglas Watson, Sylvestre C. Watkins, and Beatrice Johnson Trammell.
    - Second draft, typescript, corrected (Box 5, Folder 75)
    - Setting typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 76-77)
    - Galley proofs, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - You Can't Pet a Possum
    - Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 79)
      First version of children's story (original title Shine Boy ) with revisions and explanatory notes by AWB
  - "White Haitians"
    - Typescript, corrected, of unpublished article, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 80)
- Oversize
  - Galley proof for They Seek a City, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 81)